Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Nicholson, Samuel. Nantes
    Arrival of the Dolphin at Nantes; permission given to Capt. Brown to refit her and then to depart the port as soon as that is completed. A Guernsey privateer cruising outside the mouth of the river which they say has taken several vessels coming from South Carolina; the new ship going on very well; Mr. Williams's presence much needed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Castrioto, Felix Antonio. Paris
    Concerning certain pamphlets brought from Holland according to agreement which will be delivered to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Luce-Seillans, marquis de. Paris
    Asking Franklin to endorse a bill of exchange that he may carry out his projects at once; begs Franklin to give at the same time the promised letter of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Bedout, James. Bordeaux
    Disappointed that Franklin could not grant his request for a commission as he has been at great expense in fitting out his sloop for cruising; is determined to sail straight for New England under Dutch colors in hopes that Congress will grant him the desired commission; begs for a letter of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Benyowski, Maurice-Augustus, baron de. Versailles
    Asking Franklin to give the bearer a letter of recommendation so that after his arrival he may find military employment. Hopes to meet Franklin soon for his revenge at chess.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 26; A.L. 4p.; [Sowden, Benjamin]
    Copy of letter of August 25th (XLIV, 17). Fears the letters between them are being intercepted. Received the report that Boston and Philadelphia are captured, but this is not verified.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] September 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Baynes, John. Paris
    Informing him of a safe opportunity to send his letter to London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Fendrich, Alex
    The bearer is a native of Strasbourg; desires to serve as a volunteer on an American vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 September 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Acknowledging the receipt of the commission and instructions from Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Bert de Majan, —, abbé. Molsheim
    Begs for news of his brother, whom they have not heard from since his departure; asks that the enclosed letter may be forwarded to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 1; A.L.S. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    Recommends to Franklin a clergyman who has received a letter from Ireland to be forwarded to Albany in America and desires to know the best way of sending it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 1; D. 3p.; The Economic Society of Berne
    Programme of a contest to be held for a prize essay outlining a plan or scheme of legislation for criminal affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. Paris
    His purpose to load two or three vessels at Lisbon with salt and send them to some one of the United Colonies; desires passports to protect said vessels from being captured by American cruisers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Recommends le Chevalier de la Pottère, and begs him to do for this young man what he has often granted in less deserving cases.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Castle, Joy. Bordeaux
    Has got his ship and will sail for Virginia very soon; is obliged to leave his wife in Bordeaux until his return owing to her bad health. Desires a pass to protect his valuable cargo.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Bancroft, Edward. Paris
    Details the events which led up to his being summoned to Paris by order of the Committee on Secret Correspondence to aid the Commissioners by giving information of English affairs; for nine months endeavored to be useful to the United States; flattered himself that he would have received some regular appointment from Congress; being disappointed in this and his fortune not permitting him to accept honors without benefits he has decided to withdraw from all political pursuits.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 3; A.L.S. 1p.; de la Vérité, Chevalier. Vaureas
    So far, M. le Comte de Bruges has received no answer to his application for letters of recommendation on behalf of a young officer; high position and illustrious connections of the Comte de Bruges merit more attention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Thornton, J. Paris
    Encloses the latest papers brought by him Dicppe; willing to undertake any commission however hazrdous.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 4; A. Mem. 2p.; Yart, Abbé. Rouen
    In praise of Franklin on his arrival in France (poem, 3 p., in French), and an imaginary address made by him to France, Holland and Switzerland.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 6; A.L.S. Benj[ami]n Harrison et al. 12p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. York, Pa
    Detailed account of the war in America for the last two months.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II 396.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 6; A.L.S. Ben[jami]n Harrison et al. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. York, Pa
    Relative to a foreign loan, and to the mode of raising it by appropriation of vacant land.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 400.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Gordon, William
    Has forwarded three anniversary sermons designed for Franklin, Deane and Lee; congratulates Franklin on the great and important news that the express will bring him; trusts this event will bring G[reat] B[ritain] to her senses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowman, J. Paris
    Writes for information concerning the use of fixed air as a solvent of stone in the bladder.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Bruges, comte de. Valréas
    Wrote a month ago concerning M. d'Alençon; begs for an answer to his request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1778; A.L.S. 1p.; Condorcet, marquis de
    Requesting a letter of recommendation for M. Abadie, a young lawyer going to Boston. Messages from the Duchess d'Euville and her family. Refers Franklin to the notice of his works, written by him (Condorcet) in the volume of the Academy of Sciences of 1773.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 8; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Doerner, ----- Jr. Paris
    Asking Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to Sir James Jay, who, he believes, is at Spa in Germany.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; King, John. Nantes
    Expects to sail in nine days; will take charge of any letters, etc., destined for America. J. Gruel and Co., the only firm willing to advance their credit in behalf of the State of Virginia. Gives the signals to be observed at Cape Henry for those ships going to Virginia. Gives the signals to be observed at Cape Henry for those ships going to Virginia and Maryland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter to M. de Chaumont and a bill of exchange drawn on him; not a moment to be lost in its presentation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 10; A.L.S. 7p.; Thompson, Thomas. Port Louis
    The arrival in France of two Continental frigates under his command; the Raleigh and the Alfred; the ships in need of repairs and military stores; would be glad of advice from Franklin; disposition he will make of his prizes. Latest news from America; Howe's fleet hovering about, not knowing where to land. Ticonderoga a cursed affair. Movements of the army near Albany. Avarice and loss of virtue among the people; some parts of the continent in a seemingly lethargic condition. Arrival of small vessel from Portsmouth; boarded and searched by English frigate and obliged to throw overboard all the mail. Heavy losses experienced by Burgoyne.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requesting a letter of recommendation for M. Sollicoffre, who sails shortly for Virginia. He is an upright, deserving young man who has been several years in the counting house of Mr. Schweighauser. Is induced to ask this from his friendship for Mr. Sollicoffre.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Capt. Nicholson gone to L'Orient to aid the captains of the two frigates just arrived there. Return of the Mère Bobie. Her Captain delivered your dispatches in safety, but has not been so fortunate with those he was charged with in return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Walter, Henri. Hildeshein
    Lives in a country which produces immense quantities of linen and cotton fabrics which may be useful to the Congress; asks Franklin to procure him orders.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Captain Brown wishes to be excused from taking the Dolphin as his owners have directed him to return in the Mars, which belongs to them, but he will do as you wish. Now getting in her new mast. Would be glad if the Dolphin were not to sail 'till the Lion is ready; 1000 fuzils arrived from Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 16; L. 3p.; Lee, William
    Relative to the price of nonpareil letters, in Harlem, and the purchase of type. Inadvisable to have the entire Bible in type at once. Cause for not signing name. Glad to hear that the military brute P—t is, for a time, deprived of his power to exercise his natural insolence. Wishes he was the only British officer in America who could be justly charged with brutality. Fears for America and equally for the dear bought liberties of England, which will inevitably expire by the same wounds that destroy those of the Colonies.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 18; L. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. York, Pa
    Gates's victory over Burgoyne at Saratoga. Shipment of English merchandise in French bottoms.
    (Conclusion missing.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 412.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Afraid his letter of the 9th, enclosing one of M. Chaumont, has miscarried; begs for a line to allay his uneasiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Rolandeau, -----. Bordeaux
    His ardent desire to enter the American service; anxious to obtain a letter from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Champigny, Jean Bochard de. Amsterdam
    Sending him the second volume of his "Histoire d'Angleterre."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Elmsley, P. Paris
    Will Franklin continue his subscription to Jacquin's Hortus Vindobonensis; sets out for London on Wednesday; has Franklin any commands for his literary friends there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 20; A.L.S. 2p.; La Bastide, -----. Fontainebleau
    Offering his services to the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Thompson, Thomas. L'Orient
    Disposition he has made of the prizes; difficulties in the way of making haste.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Passy
    Goes to a rendezvous with Messrs. Chaumont and Holker; the latter desires the letters Franklin promised him. Dr. Bancroft has returned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Hirschberg, Charles de. Strasbourg
    Is professor of English at the University of Strasbourg; has translated Franklin's Examination in Parliament 1 and followed the text as closely as possible; offers his services in case Franklin desires to have any of his other works translated.
    1 See Ford's Bibliography of Benjamin Franklin, p. 133, C., 296.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Baumann, Martin. Kirchheim, Poland
    States that a brother of his went to America twenty-eight years ago and settled in Delaware, Pennsylvania. Writer and a younger brother followed ten years ago. Younger brother entered American army and rose to a captaincy. Writer returned to his native city two and one half years ago to receive an inheritance. Wishes to return to America and epouse patriots' cause. Asks Dr. Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L. 12p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Congratulates him on the surrender of General Burgoyne; account of the surrender and the military movements which led up to it; behavior of the American soldiers; skirmishes around Philadelphia. Effect of Burgoyne's surrender on Great Britain and other European countries, and on America. Urges Franklin to secure loans for America. (Conclusion missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Walker, Thomas. Boston
    Congratulating Franklin on the success of the American arms in the Northern Department; introducing Col. de Masasquelle, a member of the Royal Academy of Sciences, to Franklin's notice; his son a colonel in the American artillery and pensioned for life by this State, in consideration of his having introduced the art of founding and boring cannon solid, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Announcing the capture of Gen. Burgoyne and his entire army. Introducing the bearer of the good news, Mr. Jonathan L. Austin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    His only daughter married to Joseph Hixon, Esq., of Monsterrat in West Indies; he left Boston in the spring for London; begs Franklin to forward him the enclosed letter from his wife; should accident bring Mr. Hixon to France, asks Franklin's notice for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Biancourt, — (commission seeker). Fontenay
    His former military services; his desire to enter the American army with the rank captain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Austin, Benjamin. Boston
    The surrender of Burgoyne and his whole army to Gen. Gates has induced the council of Massachusetts to forward an express to the Commissioners at Paris; his son the bearer of this intelligence; begs Franklin to grant him his friendship and countenance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Guienne Dumouchel, Jean-Baptiste-Eléonor de (commission seeker). Dieppe
    Desires to obtain a company of infantry or dragoons in the service of Congress.
    ( In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Greene, Catharine. Boston
    Mrs. Collas is exceedingly well and quite contented to be delivered from Howe's ravages. Supposes he has heard that Mrs. Bache has a fine daughter; leaves the great news to more intelligent pens; begs for a letter if only a line.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Harold, Edmund de (commission seeker). Dusseldorf
    Offers his services; does not wish to quit his present soild establishment until he knows what conditions he may expect; his former military services; well known to any officer in the Irish regiment in France; a great friend of Gen. Conway.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 October 29; L.S. 2p.; Langdon, John. Portsmouth. N.H
    Sends by the Continental ship Ranger the articles of capitulation with Mr. Burgoyne and a copy of a letter written by Gen. Gates to Burgoyne six days before the surrender; had the happiness to be a witness of this scene. Magnificent conduct of Gen. Gates. Howe's army in possession of Philadelphia; his situation thought to be almost as bad as Burgoyne's. Description of the retreat of the English, the horrible scenes of death and destruction and the final glorious surrender of the entire army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Wendell, John. Portsmouth
    Congratulating him on the grand events in America; what the Americans owe to Franklin's influence and counsels. His uncle, Col. Josiah Quincy, prevented from writing Franklin by the danger of the times. By the impolicy of Britain the militia of America have become disciplined troops. Britain's perilous situation. His son serving with Capt. Jones on the Ranger; if Capt. Jones should promote him, would be obliged for Franklin's support; sure the family of the wendells and Quineys are not disagreeable to him. Mentions Capt. Jones as a sensible, well-bred gentleman, who has the honor of America much at heart.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Wendell, John. Portsmouth
    Introducing Lieut. Thomas Simpson of the Ranger, a most distinguished officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Cushing, Thomas. Boston
    Introducing Mr. Jonathan Loring Austin to Franklin's favorable notice. Congratulates him on the success of the American arms in the Northern Department; news from the southward not discouraging; Gen. Howe and his army said to be preparing for a retreat from Philadelphia; Washington at or about Germantown waiting to cut him off. Wishes to know what effect Gates's success will have on England and also on the Courts of Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Gonterie, — de la. Paris
    A manufacturer of materials for soldiers' and sailors' uniforms desires to send a cargo of these goods to New England; failure of a previous attempt owing to capture; is the owner of a well-appointed vessel; desires Franklin to furnish him with letters of marque that he may carry this merchandise safely across. Served some months under Capt. Wickes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    His favor of the 25th inst. he immediately destroyed. Certain debts which he must pay. Question of putting arms on board the Lion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The demand of the Dutch merchants accorded. Believes his services can be of some use to America; risk involved in his present position; depends on him to hear as soon as possible of the success of their scheme.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 October 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Introducing M. le Chevalier du Gravier, a friend of M. Coder and an officer of artillery, also M. de Livoys, navy officer, actually in the service of America. Enmity of M. des Granges and all his employes toward Coder.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Merckle, Joh Ph. Amsterdam
    Introducing M. St. Godet, son-in-law of the Governor of St. Eustatius; he is interested in all that is most dear to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 1; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Begs for the papers he mentioned to Franklin, namely: Count Vergennes's letter, the last memoir to him, the last letter to the Committee and the list of stores shipped from Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Cole, James. lle de Rhé
    Very interesting business calls him and two of his friends to Philadelphia; being unable to pay their passage thither, begs Franklin to procure it for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Gorjy, -----. Paris
    Desires to know from what source he can gain some information concerning the habits of the colonies, principally of the Quakers and the savages; these details are necessary for a work he is contemplating.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter and promising that everything shall be executed according to his wishes. Sends message to Mr. Deane.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Gayette, -------, fils. Brionde
    He and two others very anxious to join la Fayette; desires Franklin's advice and assistance to attain this end; asks for a letter from Madame de la Fayette, who is at present in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Prizes given to the English by special order of the King; money loss less serious than the excuse this will give to spies to live among them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 7; L. 1p.; Le Fevre, -----. London
    Acquainting Franklin with the fact that Miss Lydia B[ache] and her sister, of Preston, have lost their mother, and asking him to break the news gently to R[ichard] B[ache].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Luc, — du. Saint Maixent
    Madame le Baronne de la Courchambeau desires her two sons to enter the service of Congress and will make them a certain allowance and pay their passage over; begs Franklin to aid them in this affair with letters to some one in Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Anderson, John. St. Malo
    In difficulties about his agreement with M. de Purny; desires to sail in the service of his own country; asking for Franklin's advice.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 November 8; A.L.S. Richard Henry Lee and James Lovell. 1p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. York, Pa
    Bills of exchange to be presented with this letter. Henry Laurens, of Charleston, South Carolina, has been elected President of the Continental Congress.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 423.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 10; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; The Continental Congress
    Instructions to the American Commissioners in France and Spain, to purchase military supplies.
    Printed in Journals of Congress, Phila. [1778], III, 488.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Valltravers, Rodolph. Bienne
    Switzerland's attitude concerning the misfortunes of England and America; possibility of a reconciliation through the medium of a just, equitable, pacifying mediator.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, Patience. London
    Parliament not to meet until more explicit accounts are received from Lord Howe; influence this will have on the case of poor Platt still confined in Newgate with others of his countrymen. Begs Franklin not to suffer Lord Stormont or any of his tools to prevent the exchange of prisoners proposed. Many young men ready to serve in the American army; mortified at not receiving a line from any of her countrymen in Paris.
    - to The Congress of the United States., 1777 November 10; A.L.S. 1p.; de Lucé, Chevalier de Marolles. Paris
      Offers his services; encloses certificates of his capacity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the orders of the French Government to hand over the prizes to the English; cannot reconcile such proceedings with common honesty; begs to know whether there is a prospect of his getting his advances repaid. Praise for Capt. Nicholson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Gianolio, François. Turin
    Desires some position connected with the commerce between America and Italy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 November 14; A.L.S. 4p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre, Martinique
    Enclosing a copy of a letter from St. Eustatius with news from America of the taking of Philadelphia by Howe; this account founded merely on reports. Should Washington have been again repulsed, thinks his army could not have behaved with that bravery which should have distinguished troops in such an important situation; what this event, if true, will mean to the English. Gen. Gate's operations in Canada.
    [Letter enclosed.]